Translator: Ahmed Gamal Auditor: Ayman Mahmoud
Chris Anderson: Elon, welcome back to TED.
It's great to be here.
Elon Musk: Thanks for having me.
So, for about the next half hour,
We will spend some time
In exploring your vision of what an exciting future might look like,
And that, I think, would make the first question a little comic
Why do you dig?
Yes.
I ask myself this question a lot.
We're trying to dig a hole down the city of Los Angeles,
In order to start the beginning
Why we hope it will be a 3D tunnel network
To reduce congestion.
Currently, one of the most frustrating things is traffic.
It affects people all over the world.
Much of your life is lost.
This is terrible.
Especially in Los Angeles.
(Laughter)
I think you brought it with you
The first visualization will be shown.
Can I show it?
Yes, of course, this is the first time ...
Just to clarify what we are talking about.
There are a few important basic things
To create a 3D tunnel network.
First, you must be able
On merging the entrance and exit of the tunnel
Seamlessly with the architecture of the city.
By elevator,
Something like a car platform on an elevator
You will be able to integrate the inlet and outlet with the tunnel network
Using only two parking spaces.
Then the car is placed on a platform.
There is no top speed;
So we design this to work at speeds equal to 200 kilometers per hour.
How many?
200 km per hour, or about 130 miles per hour.
That is, you will be able to go, for example, from Westwood to Los Angeles Airport
In 6 minutes .. 5 to 6 minutes.
(clap)
So maybe in the beginning
It will resemble a pathway with charging points.
Yes.
Which I think will relieve some of the crowding
On the surface roads as well.
I don’t know if you noticed this in the video,
But there is no limit to the number of tunnels levels that can be reached.
You can go deeper than you can get up.
The deepest mines are much deeper than the tallest buildings.
So you can reduce any random level of urban congestion
Using the tunnels network.
This is a very important point.
One of the main drawbacks of tunnels is that if you add a layer of tunnels
Just to reduce congestion, the void will be exhausted,
And you will return back to where you started, to congestion again.
But you can reach any number of tunnels,
And any number of levels.
But people think that drilling is usually very expensive;
This would end this idea.
Yes.
Well, they are right.
To give you an example, the Los Angeles subway stretch,
Which I think spanned 2,5 miles.
It was created at a cost of $ 2 billion.
That's about a billion dollars a mile, to build the Los Angeles subway line.
This is not the most beneficial underground line in the world.
So yeah, tunneling is usually very difficult.
I think we should get at least a tenth
Of the cost of digging a mile.
How can you achieve this?
In fact, if you only do two things,
Then you can reduce the cost to about a tenth
And I think you can go beyond that.
The first thing to do is to reduce the diameter of the tunnel
For half or less.
The tunnel needed for a one-lane road, in accordance with the laws,
Diameter must be 26 feet and perhaps 28 feet;
To accommodate accidents and emergency vehicles,
And to allow adequate ventilation for combustion engines.
But if you reduce this diameter to the one we seek,
It's 12 feet, that's more than enough to hold an electric platform,
You will reduce the diameter in half,
And the cross-sectional area of ​​the strip to the fourth,
The cost of drilling is related to the cross-sectional area;
This means that the cost has been reduced to nearly one-fifth so far.
In addition, tunnel boring machines currently operate for half the time and then stop,
The rest of the time is spent adding reinforcements
For the tunnel wall.
So if you design the machine
To drill and reinforce continuously;
Doing this will cut your cost in half.
Add it to the above and you will reach the price.
Also, the machines will be far from reaching their maximum energy and thermal limits,
So you can greatly increase the machine power.
I think you can cut the cost by at least half and maybe a quarter or a half,
In addition to the above.
So I think there are a number of direct steps enough
To reach a value less than one tenth
From the cost of digging a mile,
Our goal now is ...
We have a pet snail called "Gary,"
It's the snail Gary from the South Park series,
Sorry, I mean "SpongeBob SquarePants".
(Laughter)
Gary can ...
Currently it can walk 14 times faster
From the tunnel boring machine.
(Laughter)
You want to defeat Gary.
We want to defeat Gary.
(Laughter)
It is an impatient boy,
This will make it a victory.
Victory is the defeat of the snail.
But many who imagine and dream about the cities of the future,
They think that the solution is flying cars, drones ... etc.
To go above the ground.
Why isn't this a better solution?
You will save all the costs of digging the tunnels.
Right, I prefer flying things.
I obviously are making missiles, so I love things that fly.
This is not a subjective bias against flying objects,
But there is a challenge facing flying cars
Which is that it would be very annoying,
And that the wind loads generated will be very high.
Let's just say that something is flying over your head,
That a group of cars is flying overhead,
This will not be a reassuring situation.
(Laughter)
You wouldn't say to yourself, "Okay, I have a better feeling about this day."
But you will ask, "Did they maintain the wheel covers,
Or will it fly and cut off my head? "
things like that.
So you have that vision
For future cities where these dense three-dimensional networks of tunnels are located beneath them.
Does this have anything to do with Hyperloop?
Can you use these tunnels to achieve the idea of ​​Hyperloop?
That I announced a few years ago.
Well, we were kind of having fun
On the topic of hyperlinks for a while.
We built a hyperlink demo next to SpaceX;
For student competition only;
To encourage innovative ideas in transport.
In fact, he ended up becoming the largest vacuum chamber in the world
After the Large Hadron Collider
according to size.
It was very fun to do, but it was like a hobby,
Then we thought we might ...
We built a small driving car to drive student capsules,
We will try to determine the speed with which we can make the driving car
When you pay nothing.
So we are cautiously optimistic
We will be able to make it faster than the world's fastest "bullet train"
Even in the 0,8 mile range.
Good brakes.
Yes, it is.
Either it will smash into small pieces or go too fast.
But you can imagine Hyperloop inside a tunnel
Going too long.
exactly.
Looking at the tunnel technology,
Turns out to be a tunnel,
You must..
In order to isolate it against the water table,
You will usually have to design a tunnel wall to withstand it
About 5 or 6 times the atmospheric pressure.
Reaching the void means one air pressure,
Or close to emptiness.
In fact, it turns out to be automatic,
If you create a tunnel well enough to resist the water table,
It will automatically be able to withstand discharge.
OK.
So, yes.
So you really are able to visualize
How long does Elon need in the future to operate the Hyperloop?
I think there is no maximum length.
You can dig as much as you want.
I think if you want to do something
Like Hyperloop from Washington to New York,
You would often prefer the entire path to be underground.
Because it is a high density area.
You will pass under a lot of buildings and houses,
And if you dig deep enough,
You will not be able to spot the tunnel.
Sometimes people think, it will be very annoying
There is a tunnel dug under their homes.
If this tunnel was dug
3 or 4 times the diameter of the tunnel under your home,
You will not be able to detect it during drilling at all.
In fact, if you can monitor the tunnel while digging it,
Whatever device you use,
You can get a lot of money in exchange for it from the Israeli army,
Who tries to monitor the tunnels of Hamas,
And from the US Customs and Border Protection that is trying to monitor drug smuggling tunnels.
So the reality is
That the Earth is incredibly good at absorbing vibrations,
Once the tunnel depth is below a certain level,
It becomes unrecoverable.
Maybe if you have a very sensitive seismic device,
You may be able to monitor it.
She founded a new company to do so
It is called the Drilling Company.
Very good, very funny.
(Laughter)
What's so funny about that?
How long does this take your time?
Probably..
2 or 3 percent.
I bought a hobby.
This is what Elon Musk's hobbies look like.
(Laughter)
It really is, for example ...
Basically it is the trainees and people who work part-time.
We bought some used machines.
It's kinda fun, but it's making good progress.
So there is a greater part of your time
You spend it on cars and electric transport through Tesla.
Is one of the motives of the tunnels project
Is to realize that in reality,
In a world where cars are electric and self-driving,
It may lead to more cars on the road
What time is it compared to the current time?
Yes, exactly.
Many people think that when cars are self-driving,
It will be faster and this will reduce traffic congestion
This is true to some degree.
But once shared autonomous driving is available, it is much cheaper to drive
And you can move from one point to another,
The cost of transportation by car will be better than the cost of transport by bus.
It will cost less than a bus ticket.
Therefore, driving rates will become much higher in the presence of shared self-driving,
In fact, traffic will get worse.
You founded Tesla to persuade the world
That electric power is the future of cars,
A few years ago, people were making fun of you.
Now, not much.
OK.
(Laughter)
I do not know. I do not know.
But isn't it true that almost all auto manufacturers
They have announced serious plans to rely on electricity
In the near and medium future.
Yes. Yes.
I think all auto manufacturers have a program for electric vehicles.
They differ in how serious they are.
Some are very serious about completely switching to electricity.
Some just have fun.
And some still surprisingly support fuel cells,
But I think that will not last long.
But doesn't it make sense, Elon?
Now simply declare your victory, and say "We have done it."
And you let the world go to electricity, and you go to focus on other things?
OK.
I intend to stay in Tesla in the future as much as I can imagine.
There are many exciting things that we will release.
It is clear that "Model 3" will be launched soon.
We will unveil the Tesla Half Truck.
Well, we'll mention that.
“Model 3” is slated to launch around July.
Yes, it seems very appropriate that we start production in July.
Gorgeous.
One of the things people get excited about
It is having an automatic driving mode in it.
You posted this video a while ago
Explain what this technology will look like.
Yes.
Obviously, there is an auto driving mode on the “S Model” now.
What do we see here?
This is done using cameras and GPS only
There are no "ledar" or radar systems used here.
This is done using only the "passive optical network," which is what people mainly use.
The entire road is explored
By using "passive optical network" or cameras,
And as soon as it processes the cameras data
Or vision,
Automated driving becomes possible.
If you cannot treat the vision, it will not be possible.
And so our focus is very much on getting a neural vision network
Very effective for road conditions.
Many others tend to use "Lidar".
All you need are cameras and radar.
You can undoubtedly be super using only cameras.
You can probably be ten times better than humans,
Only with cameras.
Cars currently sold with 8 cameras.
She cannot do what is shown here yet.
When will you be able to?
I think we are still on the right path to make it able to walk across the country
From Los Angeles to New York at the end of the year, fully automated driving.
Well then you're saying that by the end of the year,
Someone will sit in a Tesla car without touching the wheel,
Then click on New York and then go.
Yes.
He will never need to touch the wheel ... by the end of 2017.
Yes. Basically, in November or December this year,
We should be able to block the road from a California parking lot
To a parking lot in New York,
Without any directions at any point during the trip.
(clap)
just awesome.
But part of that is possible.
Because you already have a fleet of Tesla cars that travels all of these roads.
It collects a huge amount of data on the local road system.
Yeah, but what might sound exciting
Is that I am really very confident that she can go this way,
Even if you use variable paths on this path.
Very easy ..
If you can be very good on a specific track then this is another matter.
But she must be able to walk very efficiently,
Especially when you're on the highway,
To go anywhere on the highway network
In a specific country.
So this is not limited to Los Angeles Road to New York
We can change it from Seattle to Florida,
On this day, at a certain time.
For example, you would go from Los Angeles to New York.
Now she goes from Los Angeles to Toronto.
If we leave the rules aside for some time,
From a technical point of view only,
The time when someone will be able to buy one of your cars,
He literally leaves the wheel and sleeps
Then he wakes up to find that he has arrived.
When will this be done safely?
I think it will happen in two years.
The real challenge is not in your ability to make it work
On 99,9 percent of the time.
Because if a car crashes a thousand times,
You will often remain restless.
And of course you don't have to.
(Laughter)
It will never be perfect.
There is no ideal system,
But if we say that maybe ...
Car collision is highly unlikely
In a hundred lives, or a thousand lives,
People would say, "Okay, great, if I could live a thousand lives,
I often won't have any accident,
This is often OK. "
you, sleep.
I guess what's most worrisome to you is that people are probably
Too early they think it's safe,
And that a horrific accident might delay things.
Well, I think the self-driving system is likely to mitigate the collision at least,
Except in rare circumstances.
The thing to be aware of about vehicle safety
Is that this is a possibility.
There is a possibility every time someone drives a car
That a collision occurs due to an error.
It is never zero.
The primary approach to self-reliance is
Knowing the extent to which self-driving must be superior to humans
Before you depend on it.
But once you have achieved safe driving literally without using hands,
The potential for confusion to the industry is enormous.
Because at that time, as I said, people will be able to buy a car,
It takes you to work, then lets it go
To work in services like Uber for other people,
Make money for you,
It may cover the purchase price of the car.
So you can almost like a car for free.
Is this really possible?
Yes, that will undoubtedly happen.
There will be a self-driving fleet to share
Where to buy your car
You can choose to use the car alone,
Or you choose to only be used by your friends and family,
Or only by other 5-star drivers,
You can share it sometimes and not at other times.
This is what will happen 100%.
It is only a matter of time.
just awesome.
So, you mentioned the midterm
And I think you plan to announce it in September,
But I wonder if there is anything you can offer us today?
I'm going to show you a truck teaser.
(Laughter)
She is alive.
OK.
This is definitely a case where caution is required
From disclosing the features of self-driving.
Yes.
(Laughter)
We can't see much.
But it does not look like a small friendly truck for residential neighborhoods.
Sounds somewhat hostile.
What kind of semi truck are you?
This is a high-performance, long-range semi truck.
So it has the highest load capacity
In addition to a long walk.
The main goal is to reduce heavy loads.
This is something that people currently believe is not possible.
They think that the truck does not have enough power or it does not have enough range,
And by Tesla midway truck,
We want to show them that this is wrong, as the electric truck
In fact, it can generate more torque than any semi-diesel truck.
If you do a tug-of-war,
Tesla's semitrailer pulls the diesel truck up a ramp.
(Laughter)
(clap)
This is so cool. In the short term, this is not self-driving.
Rather, they will be trucks that truck drivers drive.
Yes, what would be fun about her
The presence of a flat curve between the torque and the number of turns per minute, in the presence of an electric motor,
While in the presence of a diesel engine or any car powered by an internal combustion engine
You will get a hill curve.
So it will be a very graceful truck.
You can drive it like a sports car.
There is no transmission. As if it is a single speed.
A great movie about that will be made somewhere.
I don’t know what it is or will end well,
But it's a great movie.
(Laughter)
Her driving test was very strange.
When I was driving the prototype of the first truck.
That was really weird, because you drive
With great craftsmanship, you are in a huge truck.
Wait, did you drive a model earlier?
Yes, I drove it around the car park,
That was crazy.
Gorgeous. This is not fiction.
I was driving that huge truck,
And I'm doing crazy maneuvers.
that's cool. Well, let's go from a very aggressive picture
To a somewhat less hostile picture.
This is just a nice house from the series "Desperate Housewives" or something like that.
What is going on here?
Well, that shows a picture of the future
Which I think will evolve.
There is an electric car in the corridor.
If you look between the electric car and the house;
There are 3 wall batteries hanging on the side of the house,
Then there is the roof of the house, which is a solar roof
That is, it is a true solar panel roof.
OK.
This is a picture of a real home, in fact, it is a real fake house.
This is a real fake house.
(Laughter)
So these roof panels,
Some of them actually have solar energy, the ability to ...
Yes, solar panels
You can adjust its style and color
Up to a very subtle level,
There are also very small holes in the glass,
So that if you look at the ceiling from street level
Or near street level,
All panels look the same
Whether there is a solar cell under it or not.
So you see a regular color
When you look from the ground level.
If you look at it from a helicopter,
You can actually look through it and see
Some solar panels have a solar cell underneath, and some do not.
You wouldn't know this from street level.
You put it in the panels exposed to most sunlight,
Which makes the plate prices reasonable, right?
It wouldn't be much more expensive than just a regular roof.
Yes.
We are sure to cost the roof
In addition to the cost of electricity ..
Solar panel roof will be less expensive than normal roof
Plus the cost of electricity.
In other words,
It would be easy economically,
We think it will look great,
It will last ..
We thought to make the guarantee endless,
But people thought
That might sound like we're talking nonsense.
But in fact, this is toughened glass.
After the house collapses,
And nothing remains,
The glass panels will remain intact.
(clap)
I mean, that's cool.
I'm going to release this in two weeks, I think,
Four different types of ceilings.
Yes, we will start by issuing two types, initially,
The other two will be issued early next year.
How big are your ambitions?
How many homes do you think may become covered with this type of roof?
I think at the end of the day,
Almost all homes will have sun roofs.
What needs to be taken into consideration is the timeframe
Which will often be around
40 or 50 years old.
On average, the roof is replaced every 20 to 25 years.
But you do not start to replace all ceilings immediately.
But in the end, if we can speed things up
Almost 15 years from now.
It would be uncommon to have a roof with no solar cells.
Is there something that people can't understand about this?
Because of the change in cost, and financial matters related to solar energy,
Most homes already have enough light for their roofs
To cover almost all of their energy needs.
If you can catch the energy,
It will cover almost all of their energy needs.
Electricity grid may be left.
It depends on where you are,
And the size of the house relative to the roof area,
But it is acceptable to say
Most homes in the U.S. have enough roof space
To provide all the energy needs of the home.
So, the decisive factor in an economy
Cars, semi trucks, and those homes
Is the low price of lithium-ion batteries,
This is what you bet on Tesla.
In many ways, this is often the center of your strength.
You have decided
That you are to maintain that strength;
You must build the largest factory in the world
To double the global production of lithium-ion batteries,
By this boy. What is that?
Yeah, this is Gigafactory,
What the plant "Gigafactory" reached.
In the end, you will be able to see
Something like a diamond
And when it's complete, it will look like a giant pile,
Or this is the idea behind it,
It is aligned with the true North.
This is one of the small details.
Will be able to produce, upon its completion,
About 100 GWh of batteries per year
100 GWh. And maybe more, but yeah.
And they are already produced now.
They are already produced. - You posted this video.
Was it accelerated?
This is the lazy version.
(Laughter)
How fast is he actually?
When it is running at top speed;
You cannot see cells without flashing.
Just something blurry.
(Laughter)
One of your basic ideas about what will make the future exciting
Is to have a future where we don't feel guilty about energy.
Help us visualize this.
How many "Gigafactory" factories are needed to get there?
About a hundred, approximately.
Not 10, not 1000.
So probably 100.
I see it's amazing
That you can imagine what it takes
To keep the world away from the massive use of fossil fuels.
You build one,
Its cost is 5 billion dollars
Next may cost 5 to 10 billion dollars.
It's great that you can imagine this project.
You are planning in Tesla to announce other manufacturers this year.
I think we will announce sites
Between two to four "Gigafactory" later this year.
Yes, often four.
Gorgeous.
(clap)
Are there no more teasers for us about that?
For example ... where? which continent?
You can answer no.
We must head to the global market.
OK.
(Laughter)
that's cool.
I think we should talk about ..
In fact, this is important.
And so I'm going to ask you one question in politics, just one.
I kind of got bored of politics, but I'd like to ask you this.
You have given advice to a person ...
who is he?
He said he does not believe in climate change,
There are many people who think that you should not have.
They would like to stay away from that.
What do you say to them?
Well, first,
I am a member of only two advisory councils,
Their goal is to walk around the room
And inquire about people's opinions on some things.
Therefore, a meeting is held approximately every one or two months.
This is my total contributions.
But I think that as there are people in the meetings
They call to do something about climate change,
Or about social issues.
I took advantage of the meetings that I have attended so far
In the interest of defending migration and climate change.
(clap)
If I don't do that,
This was not on the agenda before.
Perhaps nothing will happen, but I have said at least what needs to be said.
OK.
(clap)
Let's talk about CibsX and Mars.
The last time you were here,
She talked about something that looked like an incredibly ambitious dream
It is the development of reusable missiles.
You went and did it.
Finally, it took a long time.
Tell us about this. What do we see here?
This is one of our missile boosters
It returns from a very high altitude and quickly into space.
He just pushed the upper stage of the missile
Very quickly.
I think his speed might have been about 7 times the speed of sound,
Pay the upper stage.
(clap)
It was accelerated ..
This was the slow version.
(Laughter)
I thought it was the quick version.
But this is awesome,
Many of these failed
Before you finally know how to do this,
But now you do this 5, 6 or 5 times?
I think we have come 8 or 9 times.
And for the first time,
You have already managed to fire one of the missiles that landed.
Yes, the missile booster landed,
Then we prepared it to fly again, then we fired it again,
So this is the first time that a space explorer has made a second trip
The two flights were connected.
It is very important to realize that the reuse is not connected
Unless it is fast and complete.
Like a plane or a car,
Reuse is quick and complete.
You do not send your plane to Boeing between flights.
Right. This allowed you to dream of a very ambitious idea
It is sending many, many people to Mars
In 10 to 20 years, I think.
Yes.
And you designed a massive rocket to do that.
Help us realize the size of this thing.
Well, visually, you can see a person.
Yes, and this is the vehicle.
(Laughter)
If that was a skyscraper,
It would almost be, right, a 40-storey skyscraper?
And maybe a little more, yes
In fact, his momentum is ..
This design has about 4 times the thrust of the "Saturn 5" missile.
Four times the thrust of the largest human-made missile.
Yes. Yes.
- As usual. - Yes.
(Laughter)
Compared to the 747, the 747 has a momentum of nearly a quarter of a million pounds.
That is, for every 10 million pounds of momentum
There are 40 aircraft 747.
That is, it will equal the thrust of 120 747s while all their engines are running.
Even with a machine designed to escape from gravity,
I thought you told me last time
This thing can carry a fully loaded 747,
People and merchandise, everything
Into orbit.
exactly. It can carry a 747 fully loaded aircraft with maximum fuel capacity,
The maximum number of passengers and the maximum cargo load for a 747 aircraft.
He can carry it as if it were goods.
So based on this,
You recently introduced the interplanetary system,
And that is how it was imagined.
When do you imagine this scene, after 30 years? 20 years?
For people to enter this missile.
I hope this will be in 8 to 10 years.
Hopefully, this is our goal.
Our own ambitions are exaggerated, but I think ..
(Laughter)
OK.
Although this vehicle looks very bulky
Huge compared to other missiles;
But I think the future spacecraft
This will make it look like a rowing boat.
Future spacecraft will be truly enormous.
Why, Elon?
Why do we need to build a city on Mars
With a million people in your life,
I think you said you would like to do this?
I think it is important that we have
An inspiring and attractive future.
I think there should be reasons
To wake up in the morning and want to live.
Meaning, why do you want to live?
What is the idea? What inspires you?
What do you like about the future?
And if we weren't there,
If the future does not include our interstellar existence
To become a multi-planet species,
I consider it very frustrating
That is not the future we get.
(clap)
People just want to make a choice,
Because there are so many miserable things happening on the planet right now
From climate to poverty, you know, choose from many,
This looks like distraction.
You shouldn't be thinking about this.
It should solve what is here and now.
And to be fair, you really did a good job of doing that
Through your work in the field of renewable energy.
But why not just do that?
I think there is ..
I look to the future in terms of possibilities.
Sounds like a stream of possibilities.
There are actions we can take that affect these possibilities
Or hasten or delay something else.
Perhaps something new has been added to the stream of possibilities.
Sustainable energy will inevitably happen.
If there is no Tesla, if there is never Tesla,
It would have happened because of necessity.
It is repeated words.
If you do not have sustainable energy, this means that you have unsustainable energy.
In the end, she will run out of you,
Economic laws will lead civilization
Toward sustainable energy,
Necessarily.
The core value of a company like Tesla
Is how quickly it accelerates the emergence of sustainable energy,
Compared to what would have happened in another way.
So when I think,
What would be the primary benefit of a company like Tesla,
I will say, I hope,
If you accelerate this by a decade, perhaps more than a decade,
It would be a very good thing to happen.
This is what I consider
The primary benefit for Tesla.
As for us to become a multi-planet species and civilization traveling through space.
This is not a must.
It is very important to realize that this is not necessary.
I think the future of sustainable energy is largely inevitable,
But becoming a civilization traveling through space is certainly not inevitable.
If you look at the progress of space,
In 1969, we were able to send a person to the moon.
Then we got our space shuttle.
The shuttle can only take people to a low orbit around Earth.
Then the space shuttle stopped,
The United States can no longer send anyone to orbit.
This is the trend.
The trend is like nothing goes down to nothing.
People make mistakes when they think
The technology is developing automatically.
It does not develop automatically.
It only develops if a lot of people work hard to make it better,
In fact, I think it will retreat on its own.
When you look at great civilizations like ancient Egypt,
They could build the pyramids,
Then they forgot how to do it.
And the Romans after that, they built amazing water canals.
Elon, it seems to me when I listen to you
And look at the different things you did
You have a unique double incentive about everything
I think it is interesting.
The first is the desire to act to advance humanity’s long-term interest.
The other is the desire to do something exciting.
It seems that you feel you need to push each other.
By Tesla, you want to achieve sustainable energy,
So you make these exciting and cool cars to do that.
Solar energy, to reach it,
So you make these beautiful ceilings.
We haven't even talked about your latest thing,
We don't have time for that.
But you want to protect humanity from evil artificial intelligence,
So you're going to create a great brain-automatic communication interface.
To provide us with infinite memory, the possibility of teleportation, etc.
On Mars, it appears that what you are trying to say is:
Yes, we want to save humanity
And to have an alternative plan,
But we also want to inspire humanity,
This is one way to inspire.
I think my values ​​of beauty and inspiration
They are not valued enough,
No doubt.
But I want to be clear.
I am not trying to be the savior of anyone.
This is not what ..
I am just trying to think of the future
Without being sad.
(clap)
a beautiful saying.
I think all of here is agreed
As no ...
None of this will inevitably happen.
And the fact that you dream about these things in your mind,
You dream of things that no one else would dare dream about,
Or no other person is able to dream
With the same level of complexity you dream about.
The fact that you do that, Elon, is great.
Thanks for helping us all to dream bigger dreams.
But you'll alert me if it starts to get real crazy, right?
(Laughter)
Thanks, Elon Musk, that was pretty cool.
That was really cool.
(clap)