Translator: Hamzeh Koumakli Auditor: omar idmassaoud
I am completely comfortable in this place.
Do not misunderstand me,
My heart was beating so hard that I was surprised not to hear its beating.
I feel lightness in my head
My hands are a little sweaty.
Fortunately, I am not just used to this
I even enjoy it.
(Music)
During my career as an air player
I learned to listen to these signs my body makes,
Its main purpose is to keep me alive.
This inner feeling of fear can be the source of the pleasure.
Why do you think we ride a roller coaster?
Or do we watch horror movies?
Or fly in the air like I do?
But these moments are not enjoyable unless you choose.
Those who enjoy watching horror movies know that they can look away.
And when I fly in the air
To hold my colleague's hand while we are high in the circus tent,
I can choose to drop my hands and fly to him if I trust he will catch me.
Listening to these signs is a very important life skill
For everyone, not just my thrillers.
If we don't know how to listen and respond to signs of fear
We are in danger of submission
To respond by confrontation, flight, or inertia.
When I teach circus skills
I notice that my students feel these feelings every day.
And when they feel it
Because there is a special opportunity to talk to them about it,
To recognize and trust these feelings
They also learn how to say no when they are not comfortable with something.
This is a great base
To connect with our bodies in various situations
It is neither intimidating nor strange.
It is natural and thoughtful.
Because I'm actually not just teaching circus skills
I'm even teaching consent how to get too.
In addition to teaching me circus skills
I am fortunate to work with hundreds of young men and women every year
As a teacher of the fundamentals of preventing sexual violence.
I hear their stories straight from them
I know from statistics and from my experience
Most of the survivors know who violated them
There are high rates of adolescents who have been subjected to sexual violence by their partner,
Anyone they are dating.
Young people want to know how to talk to their partner about intimacy.
The more you help teens understand sexual consent
I realized that learning to play in the air can help us with our lives on Earth.
So let me explain to you what I mean by teaching consent through the circus.
Imagine that you are sitting for the first time on an acrobatic swing.
The traditional instructions for you will be as follows:
Well, you have to cross your feet over the bar.
And climb on the rope using your hands
Then pull yourself up until you sit down
And never let go. "
This method pushes the learner forward without discussing it with him
Also, this method focuses on what the teacher wants from the student.
This way I tell them how and when to move their bodies,
Ignoring their comfort or fear.
This instills fear in the hearts of beginners and prompts them not to return again.
While the way I talk to my students
It gives them a lot of attention
I make sure that they know exactly what will happen
And they are ready
They are part of the conversation that we have.
Addy Delaney: How are you feeling now? Student: Really fine.
ADI DELANI: I feel like you can do it. Do you want to give it a try?
Student: Okay. Adi Delaney: Yeah, like that.
Adi Delaney: Yeah, but with the soles of your feet.
Just like that, yeah.
this is beautiful. How do you feel now?
Student: Wonderful. Adi Delaney: Really cool, okay.
Well done, I'll put my hand on your back ...
Here you are.
I'll support you by your foot, and then I'll put my hand here.
Do you feel that you can put your hand on the penis?
I'll keep catching you.
how do you feel? Are you comfortable?
Student: Yes?
ADDE DELANI: I can protect you if you lean forward or backward, see?
Here I caught you!
(Audio commentary) ADD Delaney: That kind of talk
Like, "How do you feel?"
May I put my hand here? "
Contributes to the success of circus acrobats.
And I think it reduces the risk of accidents,
This is the result of the confidence my students feel
And their ability to act on their opinion and feelings
At any time.
This characteristic is necessary in life in general
When seeking intimacy with someone,
But because it is not a normal part of our behavior
It may sound very strange
Some may think that it is easier to reduce speech.
But the lessening of speech creates mystery
It creates problems and may cause violence and abuse.
There is, of course, no set standard method for requesting approval.
The words and dialect you use are your own.
It is a simple modification of our speaking method to add a request for approval
Every time we have a relationship with someone's body, whether it's intimate or not.
For example
Use "I" when talking about how you feel.
And use questions more than declarative sentences when you are talking to someone else.
And when you are in an intimate relationship
Check out the other one, such as asking, “Does this enjoy you?
Do you like that? "
In addition to telling your partner what you need, want, or love,
This helps us make these moments unforgettable
And do not regret it later.
We must broaden our understanding of consent
And to start looking at it as verb
It is not a name.
Consent is an ongoing and effective agreement
And it is not just a square that should be pointed out.
When we talk to young men and women
We will have a chance to educate them
How to communicate with concern for the other person
And check the other and respect him and his feelings and his will.
If we make consent a normal thing in everything
It's by the time someone is ready for sex
He will know that he has the right to ask questions
And stop whenever he wants
And most important of all
To enjoy these moments.
Children are our future,
And they will learn how to show concern just as we do.
Seeking consent during sex doesn't necessarily have to be a killer of pleasure
Nor does the definition of sexuality.
Rather, it can be - as in a circus - fun, joyful and joyful.
Our intimate relationship doesn't just have to be safe
It should be as exciting as flying in the air.
thank you.